<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The antimoniall cup twice cast: or a treatise concerning the antimoniall cup, shewing the abuse thereof. First, written in Latine by Iames Primrose Dr. of physicke, in consideration of a small pamphlet set forth by the founder of the cup. Translated into English by Robert Wittie, Master of Arts, Philiatr</title>
            <title>De calice ex antimonio sive stibio. English</title>
            <author>Primerose, James, ca. 1598-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101194</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837016</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837016</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1320</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10126)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 971:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The antimoniall cup twice cast: or a treatise concerning the antimoniall cup, shewing the abuse thereof. First, written in Latine by Iames Primrose Dr. of physicke, in consideration of a small pamphlet set forth by the founder of the cup. Translated into English by Robert Wittie, Master of Arts, Philiatr</title>
                  <title>De calice ex antimonio sive stibio. English</title>
                  <author>Primerose, James, ca. 1598-1659.</author>
                  <author>Wittie, Robert, 1613?-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [i.e. 30], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. A[lsop] and T. Favvcet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of "De calice ex antimonio sive stibio", which was printed as part of Book 4 of Primerose's "De vulgi erroribus", 1658.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the antimoniall cup.</note>
                  <note>Page numbers 13-16 omitted from pagination.</note>
                  <note>With a final imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Antimony --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1320:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1320:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>TIMONIALL Cup twice caſt: Or, A TREATISE concerning the <hi>Antimoiall</hi> Cup, ſhewing the abuſe thereof.</p>
            <p>FIRST, Written in <hi>Latine</hi> by IAMES PRIMEROSE D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Phyſicke, <hi>in conſideration of a ſmall Pamphlet</hi> ſet forth by the Founder of the Cup.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh <hi>by</hi> ROBERT WITTIE, <hi>Maſter of Arts, Philiatr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by B. A. and T. FAVVCET. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1320:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1320:2"/>
            <head>The Tranſlators Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving finiſhed my Tranſlation of the <hi>Popular errours,</hi> or the errours of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in matter of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, being a learned Treatiſe, lately ſet forth in <hi>Latine</hi> by <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PRIMEROSE</hi> the Phyſitian, my very good Friend, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my aforeſaid <hi>Author</hi> to write ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing touching the <hi>Antimoniall Cup,</hi> which is now adayes in ſuch frequent uſe, and ſo much admired by ſome, and to give it to me to tranſlate into into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> to be annexed to the former Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, being an <hi>Errour</hi> as common and groſſe as any other; But ſeeing that the
<pb facs="tcp:1320:3"/>Impreſſion of the aforeſaid Treatiſe a for ſome reaſons procraſtinated for a while, it was thought convenient at the requeſt of ſome Friends, to ſubſtrast this from the other, and to ſet it forth in a ſmall Pamphlet by it ſelfe, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow thou haſt, being never till now in Print; The other wanting nothing but the <hi>Printers</hi> art, ſhall as ſoone as may be, be Preſſed to doe thee ſervice; meane while accept of this lovingly, expect the other patiently, as it is tendred wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly by him, who is thine in any friendly office.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RO: WITTIE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1320:3"/>
            <head>A TREATISE CONCERNING THE ANTIMONIALL <hi>Cup, ſhewing the abuſe thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is come not long ſince into uſe a Cup made of the <hi>Regulus</hi> of <hi>Antimonie,</hi> ſo called by Alchymiſts, which is ſold at a very high rate, and is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be good for many things, and diſeaſes, both by him that makes it, and by the people who are alwayes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1320:4"/>eager in their purſuit after Novelties, and it is thought by the people to be a thing of great value, and heretofore not knowne by Phyſitians; when nevertheleſſe, it is very well knowne of all them that have any skill in the Chymicks; for the way of making the <hi>Regulus</hi> out of <hi>Antimonie,</hi> is very eaſie, ordinary, and antient. But that wee may explicate to the people this errour ſo pernitious, wee will firſt ſpeake of the Cup it ſelfe, and then of its force. Now the Cup hath not its vertue from the artificiall forme thereof; for ſo any Cup made of Silver or Gold ſhould doe the ſame. But it hath all its vertue from the <hi>Antimonie:</hi> Now they that pry into the nature of Minerals and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, are of opinion that <hi>Antimonie</hi> doth conſiſt of crude and very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure Sulphur, <hi>Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Arſenticke:</hi> And therefore it is ſo contrary to our nature, that after what manner ſoever
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1320:4"/>it be prepared and corrected, it doth even in the leaſt quantity that may be given, offer great violence to the intralls, and doth retaine its malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant quality, which can ſcarce be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by any infuſions. If by chance ſome man of a ſtrong conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution be able to indure the force thereof, hee expels it upwards and downwards, with abundance of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; but them that are waeke, and ſuch as doe vomit hardly it doth wonderfully gripe and torment; For howſoever it be prepared, it never layes aſide its malignant and deadly quality.</p>
            <p>Hence many grave Phyſitians, as <hi>Fernelius, Riolanus, Geſnerus,</hi> and the whole Colledge of Phyſitians at <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> doe utterly diſlike the internall uſe thereof, in reſpect of its deadly quality too hurtfull to Nature. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe to ſatisfie the people, we will grant, that it may ſafely be uſed,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1320:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo it be rightly prepared, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly uſed. I know it hath beene diverſly aſſayed to be prepared by the art of the <hi>Alchimiſts,</hi> that though not altogether, yet at leaſt in ſome meaſure the malignitie thereof might be abated, but that art is not yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found out, which can quite take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the force of that Medicament.</p>
            <p>Now the common and more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary preparations, which are to be ſold even ſmall ſhops, are the <hi>regulus</hi> of <hi>Antimonie,</hi> of which the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Cup is made; The glaſſe of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timonie,</hi> which the people call <hi>Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium,</hi> whereas <hi>Stibium</hi> is indeed the true name of <hi>Antimonie</hi> it ſelfe, and of this Glaſſe, not of the <hi>Regulus</hi> ought this Cup to be made, ſaith <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nertus</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> and <hi>Hartman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in his notes upon <hi>Crollius.</hi> Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there are made of it <hi>Crocus metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum,</hi> or the Saffron of mettals; <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis emeticus, Mercurius vita,</hi> a Tinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and an Oyle.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1320:5"/>And all theſe preparations are indued with one &amp; the ſame quality; to wit, vomiting and Purging, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> manifeſts that in none of the aforeſaid prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions was the deadlineſſe of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony taken away. Now ſeeing that in all things, yea even in the worſt of all there are ſome degrees of pravitie, the people muſt know that in all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, that preparation is accounted the beſt, and leaſt dangerous, in which the forme of the Mettall is loſt; for then there is made a greater ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the pure from the impure; and therefore all Alchymiſts doe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſo to diſſolve Gold, a harmleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Medicament in it ſelfe, that the forme of the Mettall being layd aſide it may be made <hi>potable,</hi> and they doe not approve of any diſſolution thereof, in which it can returne to its owne nature; which is inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d much more true of Minerals that are of a miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous nature. It is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>refore to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1320:6"/>noted that that Antimonie which we call crude, to wit, unprepared at all, is of no force to move the body, and therefore the Antients who were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of Chymicall art, knew no inward uſe thereof. Now the firſt and eaſieſt preparation of all, is that, which we call the <hi>Regulus,</hi> in which the forme of the Mettall is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, but doth melt into a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine forme of Lead. Hence <hi>Dioſcori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> ſaith, that Antimonie melted turnes to Lead, having ſome light knowledge of that <hi>Regulus,</hi> for it is made of it being melted onely, and ſo a little refined, and it doth retaine all the malignity of the Antimonie, which layd as it were aſleepe before, under the earthy excrement. This doe Mettall-men uſe, and mixe in Gunnes, Bells, and other the like en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines: but ſeeing it doth yet poſſeſſe all the naughty and miſchievous qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of Antimoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, it muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1320:6"/>follow, that the Cup made of it is moſt dangerous. Therefore the beſt Alchymiſts have quite abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it from any uſe in Phyſicke, ſave that by a further preparation may be extracted out of this <hi>Regulus</hi> the glaſſe of Antimoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and many other ſuch things farre better than the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus</hi> it ſelfe. Wherefore ſome in ſtead thereof have uſed the glaſſe of Antimonie, as did frequently that moſt excellent Phyſitian <hi>Matthiolus,</hi> the people call it <hi>Stibium,</hi> and are ſore afraid of it, where as indeed it ought to be preferred before the <hi>regulus.</hi> Nevertheleſſe <hi>Quercitanus, Hartman,</hi> and ſome others of principall note a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Alchymiſts, who doe highly extoll the vertue of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, doe thinke this preparation of the Glaſſe alſo unſafe, in reſpect of the mixture of impure Sulphur, which is not yet taken away. And therefore waving thoſe two as not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1320:7"/>ſafe, they doe familiarly uſe the <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> or <hi>Hepar Antimonij,</hi> Saffron or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Antimony; <hi>Pulvis emeticus,</hi> the vomiting powder; and <hi>Mercurius vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae,</hi> Mercury of the life: Which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations the Colledge of Phyſitians at <hi>London</hi> hath inſerted in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatory, and there is almoſt no ſhop, in which both the ſubſtance and infuſion of them is not to be ſold. From whence they that doe ſo much extoll this Cup, may gather, that they uſe a pernitious and dangerous remedy, whereas the ſame much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prepared is every where obvious, and to be ſold, yet at a very eaſie rate.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1320:7"/>
               <head>Of the force of the Cup.</head>
               <p>AS touching the force of the Cup, it doth not gently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t mightily provoke vomit &amp; ſtool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow every vomit although it bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed by the moſt gentle Medicines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe alwaies more ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Nature the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any Purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inferior parts, becauſe the ſtomacke was not made for expulſion, but for reception; for it is one of the noble parts, and of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite ſence, and hath a very great ſympathy with the Braine and the heart, in ſo much as when it is affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the people thinke and complaine that their heart akes. It is therefore not good to ſtraine ſuch a noble part with ſuch a violent medicine. But beſides, a Vomit doth offer much vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to the ſtrength of the whole Body, ſtraines the Head, braine, muſcles of the belly, the breaſt,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1320:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:1320:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1320:9"/>and all the intrailes which are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the lower belly, and ſometimes in groſſe bodies breakes the veynes, and lets out the blood. Wherefore if we muſt not uſe other purging Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, but with a great deale of care and premeditation, much leſſe Vomitories; for of all evacuations a Vomit is the moſt grievous and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. And therefore many things are to be regarded in the provoking of vomit. <hi>Firſt,</hi> the nature of the patient, and his aptneſſe or difficulty for vomiting, for in them that vomit hardly, there is a great deale of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, although they be ſicke of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, which might be cured by vomit. Such are they that are fat, thoſe that are ſtrait breſted, many ſlender per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have weake ſtomacks, ſuch are ſubject to a Cough, or difficulty of breathing, which have tumours or Vlcers in their breſts, they that have weake heads and eyes, and ſuch as are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1320:9"/>troubled with the inflamation, or paine in the Midriffe. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the time of the yeare is to be conſidered; for it is not convenient at every time of the yeare. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the nature of Diſeaſes; for in ſome diſeaſes it doth more hurt then good, and in thoſe wherein it may doe good, it muſt not yet be alwayes uſed, and therefore the founder of the Cup is miſtaken, when hee ſaith, that the Cup is good for all the Diſeaſes, which ſtand in need of Purging, as we ſhall manifeſt afterwards. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Diſeaſes; for it cannot be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred at all times of diſeaſes with out danger to the patient: The Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian muſt conſider in all Evacuations the beginning, increaſing, ſtate of the Diſeaſe, much more in a Vomit. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> great care is to be had of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the body and the humours, and many things are to be regarded both before the vomit, and in the very act
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1320:10"/>of vomiting, which are not to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in this place. So as there is no evacuation, which requires ſo much conſideration, as that which is done by vomit. Now ſeeing theſe things can be knowne onely by a Phyſitian, and that not every one, but by a very learned and sklfull man, I cannot but wonder at the adventurous raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſome men, yea and women, who being unread in the rules of Phyſicke, groſſely ignorant both of Diſeaſes and their cauſes, their times, and not knowing the method of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, dare nevertheleſſe vexe and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch a noble ſubject as Mans body with variety of Medicines; <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> perſwade vnto vomit, the moſt dangerous and difficult evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all other; <hi>Thirdly,</hi> provoke it with a Minerall, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Nature; <hi>Fourthly,</hi> to doe it with <hi>Antimonie,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n which no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall is more churliſh; and <hi>laſtly,</hi> to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1320:10"/>uſe that preparation of it, which is the very worſt of all. Not that I doe altogether diſlike the uſe of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, for I have often uſed it with good ſucceſſe, but better prepared. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the founder of the Cup is to be blamed, for ſelling ſuch a cheap medicine at ſo deare a rate, the right uſe whereof he doth neither teach the people, nor I thinke he himſelfe knowes: And there tore I have known many, who by taking the infuſion of it, haue beene grievouſly tormented, and ſome that have dyed, who deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the counſell of Phyſitians have prepoſterouſly uſed it. For Phyſicke although it be in its owne nature ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good, is the hand of God, but like a ſword in the hand of a mad-man, as we have ſaid in another place out of <hi>Herophilus,</hi> in our Popular Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1320:11"/>
               <head>Of the Founder of the Cup, and the Authours cited by him.</head>
               <p>AS for the Founder of the Cup, he profeſſes himſelfe a Miniſter, and Preacher of Gods Word, that is, a man that will ſcorne to deceive any body, and will not meddle beyond his knowledge, and therefore without queſtion hee hath brought us a very Soveraigne medicine, which he made conſcience to conceale any further, though before he was borne, the thing was in uſe in another name, as appeares by thoſe Authours whom he doth cite for the patronizing of his gaines, thought they are men of ſmall note and hardly worth, to be cited. <hi>Firſt,</hi> he hath a great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Antimonie it ſelfe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling it aboue all medicines in the world; So doe they that commend <hi>aurum potabile,</hi> &amp; o all the <hi>Alchymiſts</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1320:11"/>till this Miniſter have preferred the Gold before it. It is (ſaith he) a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (according to <hi>Paracelſus</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of <hi>Mercury,</hi> Sulphur and ſalt; So is my glove according to the ſaid <hi>Paracelſus.</hi> It was firſt diſcovered (ſaith he) by <hi>Geber</hi> King of <hi>Arabia;</hi> and yet <hi>Dioſcorides, Galen, Hippocrates,</hi> and ancienter Authors b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ore <hi>Geber</hi> doe ſpeake of it: And he called it <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſia,</hi> as if <hi>Geber</hi> ſpake Latine, but <hi>Quercetanus</hi> calls it ſo indeed, <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> amongſt all the medicines that are prepared out of this minerall, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes from all except the <hi>Rugulus,</hi> in which he ſhewes his weakneſſe, for the <hi>Regulus</hi> is the weak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, eaſieſt, and courſeſt preparation of all others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore he adds, <hi>and what may be conveniently prepared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the ſame,</hi> and that I like well, for our of the <hi>Regulus</hi> may be drawn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the dowers, the glaſſe of Antimonie, the <hi>Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us metallor,</hi> and many other preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1320:12"/>and herein I adhere to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Bornettus,</hi> and <hi>Mylius,</hi> cited by him; who doe not ſay, that it is to be uſed in Phyſicke, but that it is the chiefeſt examination of Gold, and the true matter of all Flowers, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinali tinctures contained within <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony,</hi> which is true; for the flowers &amp; other <hi>Antimoniall</hi> extractions muſt be properly drawne out of the <hi>regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> &amp; the worſt of them is better then the <hi>regulus</hi> it ſelf: Then be brings in <hi>Paracelſus</hi> with the titles of <hi>Orientall ſtarre of Naturall, Spagiricall, and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticall</hi> light and knowledge. Now I am ſure no learned and honeſt man will approve of ſuch an illiterate man as <hi>Paracelſus</hi> was, approving and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing Magicall arts, which he calls the <hi>Syrups and electuaries of the Divell.</hi> But let us heare what he ſayes; In his Booke <hi>De vitâ long â, pag.</hi> 167. cited by this Writer, not a word of the Cup, but onely of the praiſes of <hi>Antimonie,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:1320:12"/>as <hi>Alchymiſts</hi> uſe to doe, that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the deſerts thereof, and that it cures the <hi>Leproſie,</hi> which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Paracelſus</hi> never performed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, but howſoever he never uſed the <hi>Regulus,</hi> or the Cup, but hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny better preparations of <hi>Antimonte</hi> then that Cup is, as appeares by the next authority cited by him out of his 6. Booke, <hi>Pag.</hi> 22. Where he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes all theſe vertues unto the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of <hi>Antimonie,</hi> the <hi>Regulus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not the eſſence of it, but amongſt all preparations the courſeſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeſt; and all the paſſages alledged out of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> doe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imate no more, but onely that <hi>Antimony</hi> is an excellent Medicine, that cures (ſaith he) the Leproſie, Cicatrices, beſides many other diſeaſes, but for theſe two I am ſure it is falſe, for neither by the Cup, not by any other <hi>antimoniall</hi> Preparation can it be performed. And I beleeve <hi>Paracelſus</hi> ſpake hee knew
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1320:13"/>not what, when he ſaith, <hi>As that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony refined Gold, ſo by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it purifies the Body of man.</hi> He muſt bee voyd of reaſon, who will thinke this compariſon true and right, as if there were the ſame reaſon for Gold a Minerall, having ſome convenience of Principles with another minerall, and the Body of man, with which it hath no convenience at all: For the fame might be as well ſaid of all Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging medicines, that cleanſe the body of man from all its imparities; but howſoever the Cup is not the right preparation of it to give to cleanſe Mans body. Hee brings a ſecond au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Martinus Rulandus,</hi> who calls his <hi>Aqua-benedicta</hi> the infuſion of this Cup, which is abſolutely falſe, and <hi>Quercetanus, Libavius, Sennertus,</hi> and <hi>Hartmannus</hi> upon <hi>Crollius,</hi> yea his owne Son <hi>Rulandus</hi> ſayes otherwiſe; namely, that his <hi>Aqua-benedicta</hi> which he commends ſo much was made of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1320:13"/>
                  <hi>Antimony</hi> indeed, but not of the Cup, but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Crocus metallor,</hi> otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hepar antimony,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liver of <hi>antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> or ſome other better Preparation; as if he did ſay, that it was the infuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this Cup, yet it is not to be uſed by every one, except they have the ſame knowledge &amp; judgment, that <hi>Rulandus</hi> hath; neverth leſſe he uſed other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines as bad as this, which he doth commend as much, as his <hi>Extractum Eſulae,</hi> which is abſolutely preferred by him before all other medicines, and <hi>antimony</hi> it ſelfe, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wing that no Medicine is good for every body. But <hi>Alchymiſts</hi> haue that property, to extoll things to the skies, but when they come to the tryall, they are found falſe, or elſe looſe their vertues in other folks hands; As for example, that it cured the Frenſie, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for in the diſſences of the head, vomiting is very hurtfull, by the conſent of all Phyſicians. That it cured the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lling
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1320:14"/>ſickneſſe, it were to be deſired but it doth not prove ſo, except that comes from the ſtomacke, the head being onely affected by the Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the ſaid ſtomacke. That it hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Impoſtumes in the Lungs, and cured the Pleuriſie it is moſt untrue; For breaking the impoſtumes in the lungs, if it be given when they are at maturity, perhaps it will, becauſe of the great ſtraining of the upper parts of the body, but another vomite may doe the like, if the man can beare it. The truth is, thoſe that have impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes in the Lungs are ſo ſhort win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they cannot beare the ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a vomit; but howſoever an Impoſtume to be broken, and to be healed are two ſeverall things, a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit may doe the former, but not the latter. Concerning the Pleuriſie; the Phyſitian, that gives ſuch a purging medicine, that workes upward as well as downeward, in ſuch a diſeaſe, is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1320:14"/>much to be blamed, for working a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rules of Phyſicke. <hi>Querce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> is ſo bold in his <hi>Pharmacopoeâ,</hi> as to ſpeake of ſuch a Cure, but not in a right <hi>Pleuriſie,</hi> but becauſe that booke is full of lyes, I will ſay no more but this, namely, that neither he, nor <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landus</hi> ever uſed the <hi>Antimoniall</hi> cup, or the <hi>regulus</hi> out of which it is made, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that <hi>Quercetanꝰ</hi> his <hi>Aqua benedicta</hi> was made of it; for he himſelfe ſayes plainly the contrary, <hi>3dly,</hi> He brings the book called <hi>Baſilica antimonij,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending <hi>Antimony</hi> but not the Cup; And to ſhew how largely theſe <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymiſts</hi> ſpeake, hee ſayes it cures the <hi>French Pox, Leproſie, Gout,</hi> and <hi>Falling ſickneſſe,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>, never a one of them ever performed, and yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Baſilica</hi> ſpeaks of that preparation of <hi>antimony</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes ſweating, as well as of others. So I may ſay the like of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius,</hi> who commends the <hi>Antimonie</hi> but no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Cup, and ſo <hi>Mylius,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>net<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1320:15"/>commends the <hi>Antimonie</hi> but not a word of the cup. As for <hi>Mylius,</hi> he is but a tranſcriber of other mens works &amp; hath compiled a mighty great vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume without any judgement word by word out of <hi>Paracelſus, Quercetan</hi> and others, and hath indifferently put in true or falſe, whatſoever he found written, ſo I will not give a ſtraw for his opinion, when he commends the <hi>antimony</hi> againſt diſeaſes, which none of them did ever cure. For <hi>Bornettus,</hi> I know him well, he wrote his booke, being very yong, and I do not thinke he beleeves, that the <hi>French Pox,</hi> and the <hi>Leproſie</hi> may be cured by thoſe meanes. Thus I have ſiſted all the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of this man in the behalfe of his Cup which prove onely that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony</hi> is an excellent medicine, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull in operation, and too power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in deed, but that the Cup is the pure eſſence of it, none of them ſay, nor will any man that hath any skill
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1320:15"/>in <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> ever affirme. Beſides he brings ſome Phyſitians living (and ſome very well known to me, but the greateſt part I know not) who (is he ſaith) have approved his Cup: I will make a good interpreration of their judgement, for without queſtion the infuſion of his Cup will worke, and ſuch bodies might be met withall, in which it hath ſo powerfully wrought that being able to beare it, they have received much good by it, but that they have ſaid that his Cup was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſafer then other preparations of <hi>Antimonie,</hi> or then other purging Medicines, and that a woman having bought it, hath alſo gained knowledge when, and in what Diſeaſes to apply it, I will not wrong their judgement ſo much as to beleeve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the vertues of the Cup.</head>
               <p>NOw to come to the vertues of the Cup, he makes a great liſt of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1320:16"/>all the Diſeaſes for which it is good, naming almoſt all Diſeaſes that have need of purging from Head to foot, without diſtinction of the ſeverall cauſes of them, the Cup is good for them becauſe it purges, and by the ſame reaſon all purging Medicines may doe the like, and are good for the ſame diſeaſes, for Nature hath provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded variety of remedies, ſome ſtrong ſome weaker, of all ſorts, that the Phyſitian may chuſe what he thinkes moſt fit for his patient, for one ſame remedy, in the ſame diſeaſe is not fit for every one. When we reade the bookes of <hi>Alchymiſts,</hi> they commend other remedies as much as <hi>Antimonie</hi> for the ſame diſeaſes. But let us a little conſider ſome particular Diſeaſes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in his <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> J doe except againſt; It cures perfectly the <hi>French Pox,</hi> the <hi>Kings evill,</hi> the <hi>Falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> as he ſaith, in the 9, 10, and 13. th Mark, which is falſe; nay J ſay more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1320:16"/>it is a very groſſe miſtake, and raſh boldneſſe in him, or any man, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the infuſion of this cup in the <hi>Plague,</hi> ſmall <hi>Poxe,</hi> ſpotted <hi>Fever,</hi> and <hi>Purples,</hi> for all violent medicines that draw the venimous humours of theſe diſeaſes within the body which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth expell to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> circumference, doe worke againſt the rules of Art. It is alſo falſe that any vomit is good for the Pleuriſie; and ſo I ſay the like of a Conſumption: If the founder of this Cup had well knowne the nature of theſe diſeaſes, he would never have ſaid ſo. Indeed where nature hath need of purging or vomiting this cup may ſerve, obſerving all that is to be conſidered in the uſe of thoſe evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations; for we doe not deny that it will worke, but this we ſay, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the worſt and vnſafeſt preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all others, it is better to uſe ſome other then it, and all thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that he brings experience for,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1320:17"/>(leaving out thoſe that have been kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by it) might have been performed by other vomits, made our of the <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony,</hi> or other ſimples working the ſame effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the manner of vſing the Cup.</head>
               <p>NOw the manner of uſing the cup ſhewes the weakeneſſe of the man, he bids to put the Cup into a pot, and cover it with liquour to be above the cup an inch or two, then to boyle it gently for two houres, &amp; ſo to keepe it warme for twelve houres, then to take a cup full of it or more, &amp; the quantity of his liquor is a pinte of Wine for two, yet it workes better ſayes he, if two or three cup-fuls be taken, and hee is bold to ſay, that it works without any violence, gives counſell if it ſhould worke three or 4. dayes together, not to ſtop it, &amp; in the end to beware of counter feit Cups.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1320:17"/>Here are as many Errours as words; <hi>Firſt,</hi> it is needleſſe to ſhape the <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> into a cup, ſeeing the Wine is not to be infuſed in the cup, but the Cup in the wine in an earthen pot. Is not a little lumpe of the ſame <hi>Regulus</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any particular ſhape, as good as a Cup of it? And if one doe ſteepe it, will it not thinke you infuſe its ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue into the liquour, as well as the Cup, &amp; beſt of all if it were in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? But thus the <hi>Regulus</hi> had beene bought too cheape, but we muſt have it a cup or a Ring (forſooth) to make the people beleeve it is not an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing. <hi>Secondly,</hi> being thus prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by boyling, makes the drink look ſo diſtaſtfully, and makes it to loſe its vertue, ſo as if a Child hath need of halfe a pint, a ſtrong man of two or three, as he ſayes. Let the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ader goe to an <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Shop in any part of the Kingdome there he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Stibium,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is <hi>Antimony</hi> in glaſſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1320:18"/>of this let him take ſixe graines weight, let them ſteep cloſely in two or three ſpoonfuls of white wine, and it will be every whit as pure as it was without any taſte, &amp; it will worke as well, and more ſafely; but if you feare the <hi>Stibium,</hi> not without cauſe, take as much of the <hi>Regulus</hi> out of which he makes his cup, uſe it as I have ſaid, and it will worke in as little quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity. Yea ſteepe the Cup in a quart of Wine cloſe without any fire, for a fourthnight, give but two or three ounces of that Wine, and it will work with a better effect. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that it works without any violence, it is not ſo, for I know many that have taken it, who have been grievouſly tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it, and this is common to all vomits, yea even when they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by the ſtrength of nature. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> it is a pernitious counſell to ſuffer a ſuperpurgation, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke to worke ſo long, if it happen
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1320:18"/>well in ſome ſtrong bodies, it is not to be thought that it will doe ſo in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one. <hi>The laſt,</hi> to beware of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Cups, is to keepe the people continually bound to him; for (ſaith he) if it be broken, bring it to him in weight, and for Ten ſhillings he will give you a new one. This is the beſt tricks of all his booke, a pound of <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony</hi> unprepared is hardly worth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſixe-pence in the <hi>Druggiſters</hi> Shop, for twelve pence or eighteene-pence more, of that pound one may have halfe a pound and more of this <hi>Regulus,</hi> what the caſting of it into a Cup is worth let any body judge, in very deed three cups of 4 or 5. ounces a piece, doe not ſtand the maker to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ten Shillings. Beſides when the cup is broken, the vertues are not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the pieces being ſteeped doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame vertue, and will worke the ſame effect, as when the Cup was whole. The mettall then being ſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1320:19"/>good cheape, and the preparation of it ſo eaſie, there is no great feare of counterfeit ones, for a counterfeit one is like to coſt more, then a right one.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I ſay, though this Cup ſhould be ſo admirable, yet it is beyond the capacity of any that is not a Phyſitian, to adapte the right uſe of it to every perſon, for all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, times, and places, as wee have ſaid already; nor doe I thinke the Founder himſelfe hath the full knowledge of theſe things.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:1320:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jmprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. WYKES.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April. 24. 1640.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
